LLOYD ACHU

Manassas, VA, | | M: 703-944-0304 | lloydachu@yahoo.com

Summary

I am an experienced procurement, logistics and supply chain specialist with excellent client and project management skills, action-oriented with a global insight and strong ability to communicate effectively with technology, executive, and business audiences. I have developed deep functional expertise across the value chain, delivering sustainable and optimized supply chains even in the midst of demand and supply uncertainties employing strategic planning and control strategies. working with large engineering establishments, I have supported the implementation of integrated solutions across multi-functional project teams for capital-intensive projects, including design, manufacturing, operations, marketing and pricing, and customer services disciplines.

My academic background and drive for continuous professional development has led me to a Bachelor's degree in Accounting from the University of Buea in Cameroon, Higher National Diploma in Business, Finance and Management from Le Groupe Universitaire ISEM-IBCG and a Bachelor's degree in Logistics and Transportation from the University of Douala in Cameroon. I am also in the process of gaining an MBA in Business Intelligence and Analytics Management at DeVry University.

As such I am skilled and experienced in ensuring that all project teams deliver high profitability ensuring targets relating to schedule, cost, scope and quality are achieved.

Technical Skills

SAP, Tableau, SQL, RHEL, Agile, Procurement, Materials Management, Materials Requirements Planning, Financial Modeling, Project Management, Change Management, Category Management, Negotiating, Cyber security.

Professional Experience

International Logistics. Cuisine Solutions Inc

10/2018 to Current Alexandria, Virginia, US

- Look through work orders to determine the amount and type of shipments due, both inbound and outbound.
- Coordinate the logistics of both inbound and outbound freight and obtain and analyze drayage quotes.
- Create and maintain effective liaison with vendors to ensure timely delivery of shipments.
- Evaluate the performance, quality, and pricing of freight vendors, and bring onboard the best in quality and pricing.
- Complete pulls and markdowns, and monitor layaway procedures to ensure that they are current and accurate.
- Lead both onboarding and selection activities, such as monitoring dashboards on a regular basis, and setting up interviews.
- Check the accuracy of freight packaging, ensuring that all packaging slips and transfer slips are available.
- Track, trace and update the status of shipments on a daily basis, using predefined systems.
- Monitor reports on a regular basis, and create and administer billing documents according to protocol.
- Meet key performance indicators to support the department, branch, and product, to meet set company goals.
- Communicate with vendors and suppliers on a daily basis to ensure delivery of shipments in an accurate and timely manner.
- Develop a thorough understanding of all data elements and interpret them as they relate to member and shopper behavior, profitability, and product development.
- Recommending improvements to boost performance and reduce costs.

- Work closely with the production and planning during all points of orders' life cycle and performance analysis.
- Design dashboards and data visualizations to communicate meaningful metrics to different audiences within the business.

Logistics, Supply Chain and Product Analyst SIDCAM (Kimberly-Clark)

05/2016 to 10/2018

Douala-Cameroon, Alexandria-USA

Key logistics professional involved in implementing and driving capability development improvement initiatives for delivering business value in the supply chain. Partnered with the supply chain operational areas, taking the lead in specialist research, project and change management in order to facilitate transformational innovation.

Key duties:

- Manage strategic initiatives to transform organizational capabilities across supply chain management
- Manage data, analyzing performance, identifying problems, and developing recommendations that support business objectives.
- Analyze the movement of goods through the supply pipeline, monitor current practices, identify and analyze gaps, and develop process improvements that will result in increased cash flows and customer satisfaction and decreased operating costs
- Evolve and extend capability assessment models as portfolio and technology change.
- Utilize analytical and quantitative methods to understand, predict, and enhance supply chain processes
- Support initiative working teams on cost-benefit assessments, driver analyses, project management.
- Assist in business case development for proposed investments and to support capability development roadmaps.
- Conduct additional ad-hoc analyses assessing complexity impact from proposed business decisions
- Stay current with customer needs and strategies
- Understand customers' systems and work processes to better understand their reporting needs and provide cursory analysis related to business reporting to identify major issues.
- Analyzing competitors in each business sector.
- Managing relationships with the key internal stakeholders involved in all Co-marketing Team projects in order to guarantee the linear execution of the final objective drawn up by each Partner.
- Monitoring of general administrative payment and Customer assistance activities linked to the adequate management of each project.
- Quantitative and business analysis to reach actionable insights and drive decision making.
- Document, maintain, and extend analytics for our products and platforms.
- Build pipelines and data-sets, synthesize results, craft automated dashboards/bots, and communicate an informed recommendation.
- Collect, validate and manage product requirements, own and perform analytics and reporting as it
 pertains to product.

Logistics Specialist Schlumberger

06/2015 to 05/2016 Douala, Cameroon

As part of the Supply Chain department, this role involved multi-disciplinary interaction and job tasks between logistics, materials management, procurement and facilities management. This included financial control and business process systems were seamlessly integrated to support the offshore oil and gas projects in Cameroon and neighboring operations districts.

Key duties:

- Manage material mobilization for offshore projects
- Overhaul material planning to include managing system stocking levels to ensure required material and critical spares are on hand when required for critical high profile projects.
- Assist with material identification and validation.
- Manage transportations budget and costs for the overhaul project
- Lead material and logistics working group for special sub-projects.

- Operational oversight of material and logistics for assigned project
- Receive purchase orders for materials that are delivered directly to the depots.
- Request and track Customer-owned Capital Spares.
- Manage inventory cycle count activities of material at all locations.
- Communicate shipment progress/movement and other equipment related matters in a consistent and timely manner.
- Maintain shipping policies and procedures.
- Gather, analyze and summarize data to prepare and develop visual charts, graphs and presentations for monthly reports.
- Participate in continuous improvement initiatives to optimize the material flow process, lean inventory levels, vendor audits, and recommend advanced technologies to achieve operating efficiencies and final customer satisfaction.

Logistics Manager Global Outsourcing Services Ltd

11/2013 to 05/2015

Douala, Cameroon

A key logistics and transportation team leader applying effective communication and project management methodology to achieve high services standards for customers while providing key inputs to the management and business development team in acquiring and onboarding new business.

Key duties:

- Lead site distribution operational processes.
- Ensure effective employee relations, provide employee coaching and development, make employment decisions and resolve employment issues through problem resolution
- Create an inspiring team environment with an open communication culture
- Drive logistics cost reduction through optimization of inbound/primary transportation, and factory warehouse operations.
- Execution of standardized logistics systems, processes, and KPI's
- Customer service improvement through warehouse and transportation loss reduction using WCM tools and methodology
- Waste reduction through warehouse improvements, transportation efficiencies, and external collaboration activities
- Provide input into and drive execution of product group and site logistics strategy
- Prepared correspondence, accounting and financial documents for analysis.
- Preparing reports by collecting, analyzing, and summarizing information.
- Initiating and approving work orders and daily functional supervision of logistics and materials handling personnel, clients and suppliers
- Verifying results by completing tests.
- Developing project estimates by identifying phases and elements, personnel requirements, and costs.

Logistics Supervisor Global Outsourcing Services Ltd

07/2011 to 11/2013 Douala, Cameroon

Logistics team member responsible for daily operational tasks in the dispatch of transportation and earth working equipment to industrial clients in various sectors including oil and gas, agriculture, power, utilities and construction.

Key duties:

- Create purchase order requisitions for customer requirements or internal equipment and facilities maintenance work orders
- Process outside work on a daily basis as needed when shipping demand is high.
- Ensure accurate and timely raw material receipts, material identification, staging of material and location identification.
- Proactively communicate shipment information regarding route changes, delays, or early deliveries to appropriate internal and external customers.
- Maintain perpetual inventory balance in MRP system via receipt and issue transactions.
- Partner with providers to ensure efficient and effective execution of defined processes.
- Re-route freight as needed to meet demands and minimize costs.

- Manage positive day to day relationships with carriers.
- Plan and conduct meetings with subordinates to ensure compliance with established practices, to implement new policies, and keep employees abreast of current changes and standards.

Procurement Assistant Standard Chartered Bank

12/2010 to 06/2011 Douala, Cameroon

Part of the bank operations team involved in the purchasing and supply department with a cross-disciplinary role in financial administration accounts payable and sourcing.

Key duties:

- Tracked all capital spending against approved capital requests.
- Sourcing materials through various suppliers
- Creating purchase orders required to procure required materials
- Ensure accurate invoicing, invoice authorizations, and internal chargebacks are processed in a timely manner.
- Write purchase orders, process requisitions, verify shipments and deliveries.
- Work with internal staff to verify accuracy of orders and maintain product reorder points.
- Update and develop purchasing policies and procedures as required, ensuring guidelines are followed.
- Responsible for the completion of Request for Proposals to current and potential business partners to supply and maintain forms, supply items, and equipment.
- Assist in the vendor selection process by collecting necessary information as needed and provide input for the selection process. Maintain an updated list of qualified suppliers.
- Work within the facilities team and assist the Facilities Manager in annual budget preparation and ongoing expense control measures.
- Assist in the procurement and maintenance of the fleet vehicles.

Education

MBA: Business Intelligence and Analytics Management

2020

DeVry University - Keller Graduate School of Management

Arlington, VA, USA

Ongoing MBA in Business Intelligence and Analytics Management focusing on effective management, evaluation, and utilization of analytics tools employing real-world applications such as data mining, data analytics and big data examination, across any industry.

Bachelor of Science: Logistics and Transportation

2014

University of Douala

Douala, Cameroon

HND: Business, Finance and Management

2013

ISEM-IBCG

Douala, Cameroon

Bachelor of Science: Accounting

2010

University of Buea

Buea, Cameroon

Cer	tific	atio	ons
CEI	unc	au	JHS

Certified Scrum Master

References

Available on request